Guide to the Americans for a Progressive Israel Records TAM.147
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Americans for a Progressive Israel Records
1937-1991
1961-1991
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Americans for Progressive Israel-Hashomer Hatzair
TAM.147
1.25 Linear Feet in one record carton and one manuscript box.
Americans for Progressive Israel was a socialist-Zionist support organization from 1947-1997. The collection contains correspondence, writings, conference materials, administrative materials, photographs, and their periodical, Israel Horizons.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in repository; provenance is unknown but was likely a gift of the organization circa 1992. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1992.018, 1992.019, NPA.2005.243, and NPA.2005.055.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Americans for Progressive Israel (API) was founded in 1947 to function as a less ideologically-based support organization by the Hashomer Hatzair, a socialist-Zionist organization. API was founded by Moshe Kagan. API's periodical, Israel Horizons, was created initially by the Progressive Zionist League in 1952. In 1997, API merged with Education Fund for Israeli Civil Rights and Peace and became Meretz USA. In 2011, Meretz changed its name to Partners for Progressive Israel. Israel Horizons ceased publication in 2011. API was active in international Zionist work, and conducted educational programs.
Related Archival Materials
Jewish American Progressive & Left Activity Web Archive, Meretz USA Partners for Progressive Israel
Scope and Contents
The collection focuses on events and issues in Israel, notably Israel's relations with the Arab world, and contains correspondence with other left-wing Israeli political parties, minutes, annual reports and other administrative material. There is also some correspondence and administrative material, including minutes and annual reports. The majority of the materials date from the 1980s. There is a significant amount of material related to its publication, Israel Horizons. The collection also holds color and black-and-white photographs from 1937 up to the 1980s. Images include photographs of Kibbutz Ein Hashofet and photographs of meetings from the 1980s from disassembled albums.
Zionists -- United States.; Jews -- United States -- Attitudes toward Israel.; Arab-Israeli conflict |x Foreign public opinion, American.; Israel -- Politics and government; Israel |x Foreign relations |z Arab countries; Records (documents); Files (document groupings); Minutes (administrative records); Correspondence.; Annual reports.; Labor Zionism |z United States.; Labor Zionists |z United States.; Americans for Progressive Israel-Hashomer Hatzair; World Hashomer Hatzair
- 8th Biennial National Conference for Progressive Israel, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agronoff, Michael A. "Jewish Identity: Dialogue with Jewish Youth" (22 pages), 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Americans for a Safe Israel "Breirah Counsel for Judaism" (23 pages), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Americans for Progressive Israel Newsletter, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Americans for Progressive Israel Projects in Israel, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Arab Vote, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Arab-Jewish Relations, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Background Bulletin, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Civil Rights and Peace Movement, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Commentary 69/1: Liberalism and the Jews, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Conference: The Middle East Between War and Peace, New Outlook (International Symposium, Washington, DC), 1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Conference: Three Years to Camp David (Tel Aviv), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1965-1987 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence: Histadrut, 1973-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: Mapam, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Efrati, Amiram, Interview with, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Executive Board Meeting Minutes, 1981-1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Flapan, Simha and Jibran Majdelang "Zionism, Racism and the Arabs (A Debate over De-Zionization)," reprint (38 page), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Givat Haviva (21 pages), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Haggadah (Pessach), undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Hakibbuz Ha'artzi/Hashomer Hatzair, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Israel and Palestine Political Report, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Israel Horizons, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Israel Horizons: Articles, Drafts, Typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Israel Horizons: Articles, Drafts, Typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Israel Horizons: Material for "Next Issue", undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Israel Horizons: Poetry, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Jewish Labor Committee Review, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Jewish Liberation Information Service, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Jewish Liberation Journal, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Jewish Liberation Project, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- The Jewish Radical (Journal), 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- La'Inyan (Journal), 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Lebanon, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Majus, Jacob. "Detente" (26 pages), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Mapam: Direct Line from Israel, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Mapam International Service, 1961-1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Mapam; London Office, circa 1964-1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Nahumi, Mordechai "Rise and Decline of Arab Guerilla and Terror" (109 pp.), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Photographs: Blue Photo Album (Originals) [1 of 2], 1980s (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Photographs: Blue Photo Album (Originals) [1 of 2], 1980s (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Photographs: Blue Photo Album (Reproductions), 1980s (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Photographs: Red Photo Album (Originals) [1 of 4], 1987 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Photographs: Red Photo Album (Originals) [2 of 4], 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs: Red Photo Album (Originals) [3 of 4], 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs: Red Photo Album (Originals) [4 of 4], 1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs: Red Photo Album (Reproductions), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Photographs with Related Correspondence, 1937-1988 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Religious Zionism, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Religious Socialism, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Sharsheret, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Shefa Quarterly, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Syrkin, Marie; "Jews and Revolutionary Movements" (pamphlet, 27 pp.), undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Tadmit Newsletter, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- Zionist Election Affair: Americans for Progressive Israel, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 49)